<para>
Serial download protocol for GPS data loggers called "miniHomer". 
These loggers are based on Skytraq Venus 5 and Venus 6 chipsets, but with modified firmware.
The miniHomer logger has five POI (or better: Point-to-Return, PTR?), which can be set programatically. The miniHomer module in gpsbabel is an extension of the skytraq module. 
</para>

<para>
Following a list of devices which should be supported by this module
(Note that not all of them have actually been tested, so if you can confirm that additional models work, please mail the gpsbabel-misc group with your success, tips, and any pertinent links for your model.)
</para>

<table id="miniHomer_devices">
<title>Devices supported by miniHomer module</title>
<tgroup cols="4">
<thead>
<row>
 <entry>Manufacturer</entry> 
 <entry>Model</entry> 
 <entry>USB (baud)</entry> 
 <entry>Bluetooth (baud)</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
  <entry>
  	<ulink url="http://navin.com.tw/miniHomer.htm"> Navin </ulink>
  	<ulink url="http://www.znex.de/minihomer-details.html">Z:NEX</ulink>
  </entry>
  <entry>miniHomer</entry>
  <entry>up to 230400</entry>
  <entry>this device does not have bluetooth</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<example id="miniHomer-on-linux">
  <title>Command showing miniHomer download of tracks and erasing the logger on Linux</title>
  <para><userinput>gpsbabel -i miniHomer,erase -f /dev/ttyUSB0 -o gpx -F out.gpx</userinput></para>
</example>

<example id="miniHomer-erase">
  <title>Command showing miniHomer erasing the logger without download on Linux</title>
  <para><userinput>gpsbabel -i miniHomer,erase,no-output -f /dev/ttyUSB0</userinput></para>
</example>

<para>miniHomer has five POI called Home, <emphasis>Car</emphasis>, <emphasis>Boat</emphasis>, <emphasis>Heart</emphasis>, <emphasis>Bar</emphasis>. You can set the lla 
(Lattitude, Longitude, Altitude) for each of the POI. The format is 
<emphasis>&lt;name&gt;=&lt;lat&gt;:&lt;lng&gt;[:&lt;alt&gt;]</emphasis>
Once the according POI symbol is selected on miniHomer, the display shows you the direction and distance to the POI.
</para>
<example id="miniHomer-on-linux-poi">
  <title>Command showing miniHomer setting Car and Home POI</title>
  <para>
  	<userinput>
  	   gpsbabel -i miniHomer,Car=36.790145:-6.352898,Home=-3.066667:37.359167:5895 -f /dev/ttyUSB0 -o gpx -F out.gpx
  	</userinput>
       Sets the Car/Home symbols' latitude longitude and altitude.
       If you select the Car/Home symbol on miniHomer, the display will show the direction and distance to 
       this location as soon as it has a satellite fix.
	</para>
</example>
