
         
         <para> The duplicate filter is designed to remove duplicate
         points based on their shortname (traditionally a waypoint's
         name on the GPS receiver), and/or their location (to a
         precision of 6 decimals).  This filter supports two options
         that specify how duplicates will be recognized, "<parameter moreinfo="none">shortname</parameter>" and "<parameter moreinfo="none">location</parameter>".  Generally, at least
         one of these options is REQUIRED.  </para>
         <example id="duplicate_to_suppress_points">
            <title>Using duplicate filter to suppress points with same name and locations</title>
            <screen format="linespecific"> gpsbabel -i gpx -f 1.gpx -f 2.gpx -x duplicate,location,shortname  \
	         -o gpx -F merged_with_no_dupes.gpx</screen>
         </example>
         <para> would remove points that have duplicate shortnames
         *AND* duplicate locations.  The result would be a GPX file
         that more than likely contains only unique points and point
         data.</para>
         <para> The duplicate filter can also take an "all" option.
         If you specify that option, all instances of a duplicated
         waypoint will be removed, not just the second and subsequent
         instances.  If your input file contains waypoints A, B, B,
         and C, the output file will contain waypoints A, B, and C
         without the "all" option, or just A and C with the "all"
         option.  This option can be useful as an "ignore list" in
         some circumstances.
</para>
         <para> Finally, the duplicate filter takes a
         "<option>correct</option>" option.  If you specify that
         option, the latitude and longitude frmo later duplicates will
         replace the latitude and longitude in earlier waypoints.  You
         can use this to apply a list of "<emphasis role="bold">waypoint corrections</emphasis>" to a larger
         file, while keeping all of the other details from the larger
         file.</para>
      
