<para> 
	GPSBabel supports a wide variety of Garmin hardware via serial
	on most operating systems and USB on Windows, Linux, and OS X.
</para>

<para> 
	For serial models, be sure the GPS is set for "Garmin
	mode" in setup and that nothing else (PDA hotsync programs, gpsd,
	getty, pppd, etc.) is using the serial port.
</para>

<para> 
	Supported models on USB include VistaC, SummitC, 60C, 60CS, 76C, 
	76CS, 96C, Quest, 2610, 2620, 2650, 2720, 2730, 2820, Foretrex 201,
	Foretrex 301, Forerunner 201, Forerunner 205, Forerunner 301, 
	Forerunner 305,  Edge 205, Edge 305, and most serial units.
</para>

<para> 
	To communicate with a unit serially, use the name of that
	serial port such as "COM1" or  "/dev/cu.serial".  
</para>
<para>
	To communicate via USB use "usb:" as the filename on all OSes.   
	Thus, to read the waypoints from a Garmin USB unit and write 
	them to a GPX file:

      <screen format="linespecific">gpsbabel -i garmin -f usb: -o gpx -F blah.gpx</screen>

</para>
<para>
	If you have multiple units attached via USB, you may provide 
	a unit number, with zero being the implied default.  So if you 
	have three USB models on your system, they can be addressed as 
	"usb:0", "usb:1", and "usb:2".  To get a list of recognized devices,
	specifiy a negative number such as:
</para>
	<screen format="linespecific">gpsbabel -i garmin -f usb:-1</screen>
 
<para> 
When reporting problems with the Garmin format, be sure to include
the full unit model, firmware version, and be prepared to offer
debugging dumps by adding "-D9" to the command line, like:
</para>

      <screen format="linespecific"> gpsbabel -D9 -i garmin -f usb: -o gpx -F blah.gpx</screen>

<para> 
Custom icons are supported on units that support that.
Neither GPSBabel nor your firmware know what is associated with any
given slot number.  They don't know that the picture you placed in the
first slot is a happy face, they only know they're in the lowest
numbered slot.  GPSBabel names the them consistently with Mapsource,
so they are named 'Custom 0' through 'Custom 511'.
</para>

