   <chapter id="Usage">
      <title>Usage</title>
      <sect1 id="Invocation">
         <title>Invocation</title>
<para>
If you're using GPSBabel, you will need to know how to do at least two things:
read data from a file, and write it to another file.  There are four basic
options you need to know to do those things:
</para>
<segmentedlist>
<?dbhtml list-presentation="table"?>
<segtitle>Command</segtitle>
<segtitle>Meaning</segtitle>
<seglistitem>
  <seg><option>-i</option> <parameter class="command">format</parameter></seg>
  <seg>Set input format</seg>
</seglistitem>
<seglistitem>
  <seg><option>-f</option> <parameter class="command">filename</parameter></seg>
  <seg>Read file</seg>
</seglistitem>
<seglistitem>
  <seg><option>-o</option> <parameter class="command">format</parameter></seg>
  <seg>Set output format</seg>
</seglistitem>
<seglistitem>
  <seg><option>-F</option> <parameter class="command">filename</parameter></seg>
  <seg>Write output file</seg>
</seglistitem>
</segmentedlist>
<important>
<para>
Case matters.  Notably <option>-f</option> (lowercase) sets the <emphasis>input</emphasis> file.  <option> -F</option> (uppercase) sets the <emphasis>output</emphasis> file. 
</para>
</important>

<para>
The <parameter class="command">format</parameter> parameters in the above list
refer to the names of formats or file types supported by GPSBabel. 
</para>
<para><userinput>gpsbabel -? </userinput></para>
<para>will always show you the supported file types.  In this document, the
various supported formats are listed in <xref linkend="The_Formats" />.  The 
name that you would use on the command line follows the format name in 
parentheses.
</para>
<para>
Options are <emphasis>always</emphasis> processed in order from left to right.
In practical terms, this means that things you want to read should appear
in the command before things you want to write.   This sometimes surprises
new users as adding options to turn on debugging at the end, for example, 
doesn't work as the debugging is turned on after all the interesting work is
done.   The reason for this strict ordering becomes more apparent once you
learn about mixing formats and filters.
</para>
<para>
The <parameter class="command">filename</parameter> parameters specify the 
name of a file to be read or written.
</para>

<para>To use
         GPSBabel in its simplest form, just tell it what you're reading, where to read
         it from, what you're writing, and what to write it to.  For
         example:</para>
         <para><userinput>gpsbabel -i geo -f /tmp/geocaching.loc -o gpx -F /tmp/geocaching.gpx</userinput></para>
         <para>tells it to read the file <filename>/tmp/geocaching.loc</filename> in geocaching.com
         format and create a new file <filename>/tmp/geocaching.gpx</filename> in GPX format.   It's important to note that the names have nothing to do with the formats actually used.</para>
         <para> This command will read from a Magellan unit attached
         to the first serial port on a Linux system (device names will
         vary on other OSes; typically COMx: on WIndows) and write them as a geocaching loc file.</para>
<example>
  <title>Command showing Linux download from Magellan serial and writing to .loc file</title>
         <para><userinput>gpsbabel -i magellan -f /dev/ttyS0 -o geo -F mag.loc</userinput></para>
</example>
         <para>This second command does the same on Microsoft Windows.</para>
<example>
  <title>Command showing Windows download from Magellan serial and writing to .loc file</title>
         <para><userinput>gpsbabel -i magellan -f com1 -o geo -F mag.loc</userinput></para>
</example>
         <para>Optionally, you may specify <parameter moreinfo="none">-s</parameter> in any command line.  This
         causes the program to ignore any "short" names that may be
         present in the source data format and synthesize one from the
         long name.  This is particularly useful if you're writing to
         a target format that isn't the lowest common denominator but
         the source data was written for the lowest common
         denominator.  This is useful for writing data from geocaching.com
         to a GPS so my waypoints have "real" names instead of
         the 'GC1234' ones that are optimized for receivers of the lowest 
	common denominator.
         A geocacher using Linux with a Magellan receiver may thus find commands
         like this useful.</para>
         <para><userinput>gpsbabel -s -i geo -f geocaching.loc -o magellan -F /dev/ttyS0  </userinput></para>
	<para>His counterpart on Windows will find this equivalent</para>
	<para><userinput>gpsbabel -s -i geo -f geocaching.loc -o magellan -F com1</userinput></para>
      </sect1>
      <sect1 id="Suboptions">
	<title>Suboptions</title>
	<para>
	  Many of the available format options in GPSBabel can themselves
	  take options.   While we try to make all the formats do the most
	  sensible thing possible without any extra options; this allows
	  great power and flexibility in the operation of the program.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Suboptions are comma separated and immediately follow the option
	  itself. The available suboptions are listed on the individual 
	  format pages.  We'll make an example from <xref linkend="fmt_kml" />:
	</para>
         <para><userinput>gpsbabel -i gpx -f file.gpx -o kml,deficon="file://myicon.png",lines=0 -F one.kml -o kml -F two.kml</userinput></para>
	<para>
	This command will read the GPX file <filename>file.gpx</filename>
	and create two KML files.    <filename>one.kml</filename> will
	have the given icon and no lines between track and routepoints.
	<filename>two.kml</filename> will be created with the defaults used
	in the KML writer.
	</para>
	<para>
	Suboptions for the various formats allow you to change serial speeds,
	pass arguments to filters, change the type of file written, override
	icon defaults, and lots of other things.   The suboptions for each
	filetype are documented on the page in this document that describes
	the option itself.
	</para>
      </sect1>
      <sect1 id="Advanced_Usage">
         <title>Advanced Usage</title>
         <para>Argument are processed in the order they appear on the command
line and are translated internally into a pipeline that data flows
through when executed. Normally one would: </para>
         <simplelist type="vert">
            <member>read from one input</member>
            <member>optionally apply filters </member>
            <member>write into one output</member>
         </simplelist>
         <para> but GPSBabel is flexible enough to allow more complicated
operations such as reading from several files (potentially of
different types), applying a filter, reading more data, then writing the
merged data to multiple destinations.
</para>
         <para>The input file type remains unchanged until a new
         <parameter moreinfo="none">-i</parameter> argument is seen.
         Files are read in the order they appear. So you could merge
         three input files into one output file with: </para>
	<example>
	<title>Merging multiple files into one</title>
           <para><userinput>gpsbabel -i geo -f 1.loc -f 2.loc -f 3.loc -o geo -F big.loc</userinput></para>
	</example>
         <para>You can merge files of different types:</para>
	<example>
	<title>Merging multiple files of differing types.</title>
         <para><userinput>gpsbabel  -i geo -f 1.loc -i gpx -f 2.gpx -i pcx 3.pcx  -o gpsutil -F big.gps</userinput></para>
	</example>
	<example>
	 <title>Writing the same data in multiple output formats.</title>
         <para> You can write the same data in different output formats:</para>

         <para><userinput>gpsbabel -i geo -f 1.loc -o gpx -F 1.gpx -o pcx -F 1.wpt</userinput></para>
	</example>
         <para>If you want to change the character set of input or/and
         output side you can do this with the option <option>-c
         &lt;character set&gt;</option>. You can get a complete list
         of supported character sets with "gpsbabel -l".  To change
         the character set on both sides you should do this:</para>
         <para><userinput>gpsbabel -i xcsv,style=foo.style -c latin1 -f foo -o xcsv,style=bar.style -c ms-ansi -F bar</userinput></para>
         <para>Note, that some formats have a fixed character set and ignore this option.</para>
      </sect1>
      <sect1 id="Route_And_Track_Modes">
         <title>Route and Track Modes</title>
         <para> Most formats supported by GPSBabel will make a reasonable attempt to work
         transparently with waypoints, tracks, and routes.  Some
         formats, like <link linkend="fmt_garmin">garmin</link> and <link linkend="fmt_magellan">magellan</link> require the <parameter moreinfo="none">-t</parameter> flag to work with tracks and
         <parameter moreinfo="none">-r</parameter> to work with
         routes. <parameter moreinfo="none">-w</parameter> is for
         waypoints, and is the default. So if you wanted to read all
         data from a Magellan Meridian GPS receiver into a gpx file, you might use a command
         like:</para>
         <para><userinput> gpsbabel -t -r -w -i magellan -f com1:  -o gpx -F backup.gpx</userinput></para>
         <para> Tracks and routes are advanced features and don't try
         to handle every possible hazard that can be encountered
         during a conversion.  If you're merging or converting files
         of similar limitations, things work very well.</para>
	 <para> Many of those hazards can be overcome with our filters
	 but there are often compromises to be made.  For example, if you
	 have a GPX route that contains  150 turn points but you're sending
	 the route to a GPS receiver that supports only 30 turnpoints, something has
	 to go.   One might use our 'simplify' filter to produce a route that
 	 retained the 30 most mathematically significant turnpoints but that
	 may not really be the route you had in mind.
	 </para>
         <para> Tracks and routes will sometimes be converted to a
         list of waypoints when necessary, One example is when writing into one
         of the CSV formats. The inverse operation is not supported
         right now, so reading the converted track back from CSV will
         always result in a list of waypoints, not the original track.
</para>
         <para> The presence of <parameter moreinfo="none">-s</parameter> on the command line tends to
         creats havoc on tracks and routes since many of these formats
         rely on internal linkages between such points and renaming
         them may break those linkages.  In general, don't use
         <parameter moreinfo="none">-s</parameter> when tracks or
         routes are present.
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="inifile">
  <title>Working with predefined options</title>
    <para>
      GPSBabel can read a file on startup to set defaults for options. All
      module and filter options may be set this way. 
    </para>

    <para>
      The format of the file is identical to the inifile-format often seen 
	on Windows.  Here is an example:
    </para>
<!--I don't know what the best "DOCbook-ese" is for this, but it's probably
  not a simplelist... rjl -->
    <simplelist columns="1">
      <member>[Common format settings]</member>
      <member>snupper=Y</member>
      <member>snlen=10</member>
      <member>[gpx]</member>
      <member>gpxver=1.1</member>
      <member>[magellan]</member>
      <member>baud=115200</member>
      <member>[tiger]</member>
      <member>[Garmin categories]</member>
      <member>; any # from 1 to 16</member>
      <member>1=fixed waypoints</member>
      <member>2=temporary waypoints</member>
    </simplelist>
    <para>
      Each section of the file starts with a '[section]' header followed by any
      number of lines formatted option=value. Leading and trailing whitespace
	will be
      automatically removed from header, option and value items. 
<!--Are there any other lines? If not, why name them?  rjl -->
      Lines starting 
      with '#' or ';' will be treated as comments and ignored.
    </para>

    <para>
	There are three optional sections.
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>Common format settings.</para>
	<para>  Any option from any of the formats listed here will be used by
		GPSBabel unless explictly provided on the command line.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>Common filter settings.</para>
	<para>As above, but for filters.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>Garmin categories</para>
	<para>This allows you to give readable names to the numeric categories
	used internally in some Garmin devices and the Mapsource formats
	such as GDB and MPS.  This is information is also used by our GPX 
	and garmin_txt formats as well.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      By default, GPSBabel tries at startup to load the file named 
	<filename>gpsbabel.ini</filename> from the following locations:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>current working directory</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Windows: all paths "APPDATA", "WINDIR", "SYSTEMROOT" declared in environment.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Unix like OS'ses: <filename>${HOME}/.gpsbabel/</filename>, <filename>/usr/local/etc/</filename> and <filename>/etc/</filename></para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
	<para>
      If the <option>-p</option> option is specified, the above locations are not searched.
      Only the filename specified by that option will be used.
	</para>
    <para>
      There may be situations where predefined values are not useable 
      (i.e. wrapper applications using GPSBabel in the background). 
       The inifile mechanism can be disabled with an empty filename.
    </para>
    <para><userinput>gpsbabel -p "" -i gpx -f something.gpx -o tiger -F -</userinput></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="tracking">
  <title>Realtime tracking</title>
    <para>
      Introduced in GPSBabel 1.3.1, we now have an <emphasis>experimental</emphasis>  feature for realtime tracking via the new <option>-T</option> option.  This reads position reports from selected formats and writes an output file when a position report is received. 
    </para>
    <para>
      As of this writing, <link linkend="fmt_garmin">Garmin's PVT
        protocol</link>  and 
      <link linkend="fmt_nmea">NMEA</link>  are supported 
	  inputs. KML, NMEA, and the variou XCSV formats are supported on 
	  output.   Additional formats may be added by interested parties 
	  later.
    </para>
<example>
  <title>Read realtime positioning from Garmin USB, write to Keyhole Markup</title>
  <para><userinput>gpsbabel -T -i garmin -f usb: -o kml -F xxx.kml</userinput></para>
  <para>
   	  Will read the USB-connected Garmin and rewrite 'xxx.kml' atomically,
          suitable for a self-refreshing network link in Google Earth.
        </para>
      </example>

<example>
  <title>Read realtime positioning from Wintec WBT-201 via Bluetooth on Mac, write to Keyhole Markup</title>
  <para><userinput>gpsbabel -T -i nmea -f /dev/cu.G-Rays2-SPPslave-1 -o kml -F xxx.kml</userinput></para>
  <para>
    Will read the Wintec WBT-201 via Bluetooth, using the name that
    the Mac assigned it, and rewrite 'xxx.kml' atomically,
          suitable for a self-refreshing network link in Google Earth.
        </para>
</example>


        <para>
          Be sure to substitute an device name appropriate for your device
          and OS, such as <filename>/dev/cu.usbserial</filename> or
          <filename>/dev/cu.BT-GPS-37A695-BT-GPSCOM-1</filename>
          for Mac, <filename>COM23:</filename> for Windows, or
          <filename>usb:</filename> for
          <link linkend="fmt_garmin">Garmin USB</link>.    These names
            (except the "usb:" parlance for Garmin USB) are assigned by
            your operating system.

        </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="batchfile">
  <title>Batch mode (command files)</title>
  <para>
	In addition to reading arguments from the command line, GPSBabel can
	read directions from batch (or command) files via the <option>-b</option> option.
  </para>
  <para>
    These files are ideal for holding long command lines, long file lists, complex filters 
    and so on. You can use all GPSBabel options and combinations when writing
    such files. Nesting batch files by using the <option>-b</option> option within a batch file is supported.
  </para>
  <para>
  Here is an example demonstrating segmenting a large command line
  by placing the input and filtering directives in a file called 'all_my_files'.
  </para>
  <para><userinput>gpsbabel -b all_my_files -o gdb -F all_my_tracks.gdb</userinput></para>
  <para>
    'all_my_files' could look like this:
  </para>
  <simplelist columns="1">
    <member>-i gpx</member>
    <member>-f saxony_in_summer_2004.gpx -f austria_2005.gpx</member>
    <member>-i gdb</member>
    <member>-f croatia_2006.gdb</member>
    <member>-x nuketypes,waypoints,routes</member>
    <member>-x track,pack,split,title="LOG # %Y%m%d"</member>
  </simplelist>
</sect1>
      <sect1 id="all_options">
	<title>List of Options</title>
  <para>
   The complete list of available options to GPSBabel can be obtained by
   running <command>gpsbabel -h</command>.  While there are a number of
   options, most people will not use most of them, so don't be intimiated.
  </para>
<para><option>-p</option> Read preferences file.   On startup, GPSBabel will look for a file named <filename>gpsbabel.ini</filename> containing preferences you have provided.  This option lets you pick a different files.  See <xref linkend="inifile"/> for more info.</para>
<para><option>-s</option> Write "smart" names.  This option influences some - but not all - of our writers to try to build "smart" waypoint names.   For example, in modules that know about geocaching, it may replace "GC1234" with the actual name of the geocache.</para>
<para><option>-r</option> Work on routes.  This option has a subtly different meaning in different cases.  As the very first formats in GPSBabel were for serial GPSes and routes and tracks were large and thus time-consuming to transfer, the default was waypoints only with this option to turn on the extra data.   Some of our file formats use this option to mean "work only on routes, even if you have tracks/waypoints", but we're trying to discourage that behavior and in most cases, consider it a bug. </para>
<para><option>-t</option> Work on tracks.  See <option>-r</option> for excuses. </para>
<para><option>-w</option> Work on waypoints.  This is the default. </para>
<para><option>-T</option> Enable Realtime tracking. This option isn't supported by the majority of our file formats, but repeatedly reads location from a GPS and writes it to a file as described in <xref linkend="tracking" /></para>
<para><option>-b</option> Process batch file. In addition to reading arguments from the command line, we can read them from files containing lists of commands as described in <xref linkend="batchfile"/> </para>
<para><option>-c</option> Select character set. This option lets you chose the character set.  You can get a list of supported character sets via <option>-l</option> </para>
<para><option>-N</option> Control "smart" output.   The <option>-N</option> actually has two subtoptions, <option>-Ni</option> and <option>-Ns</option>.   This lets you control whether a given writer will choose smart icons and names, respectively.   The option <option>-N</option> by itself selects both.    </para> 
<para><option>-x filter</option> Run filter. This option lets use use one of of our many data filters. Position of this in the command line does matter - remember, we process left to right.</para>
<para><option>-D</option> Enable debugging.   Not all formats support this.  It's typically better supported by the various protocol modules because they just plain need more debugging.   This option may be followed by a number.   Zero means no debugging.  Larger numbers mean more debugging. </para>
<para><option>-l</option> Print character sets.   </para>
<para><option>-h</option><option>-?</option> Print help. </para>
<para><option>-V</option> Print version number. </para>
      </sect1>
</chapter>
