
         
         <para> ( !!! This filter always drops empty tracks !!! )
         </para>
         <para>The track filter is a tool for manipulating track lists.  The
following options are available:</para>
         <para> TITLE</para>
         <para> Gives the new track(s) a basic title. Basic means if
         more than one track is created by filter the title will be
         expanded with the date the new track. Special formats (see
         UNIX date or strftime for details) are possible.
</para>
         <screen format="linespecific">
gpsbabel -t \
 -i gpx -f in.gpx \ -x track,pack,split,title="ACTIVE LOG-%D" \ 
-o gpx -F out.gpx PACK
	</screen>
         <para>MOVE</para>
         <para>Change the time of all trackpoints. This is useful if
         your track has moved by one or more hours through a time zone
         problem.  The following example will shift your track to be
         one hour later.</para>
         <screen format="linespecific">	    
gpsbabel -t  -i gpx -f in.gpx  \
    -x track,move=+1h,pack,title="ACTIVE LOG"  \
    -o gpx -F out.gpx 	</screen>
         <para> START / STOP </para>
         <para>Filter tracks against time borders. All points outside
         this range will be dropped. The date-time paramters have to
         be in form of YYYYMMDDHHMMSS; but you may specify only the
         most significant portion represented in the the leftmost
         fields.  See the example, where the time is specified only
         through the hour.  If you only want to get a track mapped on
         20 july 2005 from 10 am to 6pm, you should use this: </para>
         <screen format="linespecific">
gpsbabel -t -i gpx -f in.gpx -x \
      track,start=2005072010,stop=2005072018 \
      -o gpx -F out.gpx </screen>
         <para>PACK</para>
         <para> With this default option all tracks from input will be
         packed into one track. If tracks overlaps in time, the filter
         stops working.  To pack all the tracks together into one
         track and give it a name, use this:</para>
         <screen format="linespecific">	    
gpsbabel -t  -i gpx -f in.gpx  	-x track,pack,title="ACTIVE LOG"  \
		     -o gpx -F out.gpx 	</screen>
         <para>SPLIT </para>
         <para> The input track will be split into several tracks
         depending on date of track points. If there is more than one
         track, use the pack option before before using this.  To
         split a single tracks into separate tracks for each day and
         name them, use this:
      </para>
         <screen format="linespecific">
gpsbabel -t -i gpx -f in.gpx -x \
   track,split,title="ACTIVE LOG \
    # %Y%m%d" -o gpx -F out.gpx</screen>
         <para> If the input has multiple tracks, pack them together before
splitting them back apart per day thusly: </para>
         <screen format="linespecific">     	    
gpsbabel -t   -i gpx -f in.gpx  \
     -x track,pack,split,title="ACTIVE LOG # %D"  	\
     -o gpx -F out.gpx</screen>
         <para> Additionally you can add an interval to the split
         option.  With this the track will be split if the time
         between two points is greater than this parameter. The
         interval must be numeric and can be int days, hours, minutes
         or seconds, expressed as one of the character "d", "h", "m",
         or "s".  If no trailing character is present, the units are
         assumed to be in seconds.
</para>
         <para> For example, to split a track based on an four hour
         interval, use this:</para>
         <screen format="linespecific">            
gpsbabel -t \ 
     -i gpx -f in.gpx \ 
     -x track,pack,split=4h,title="LOG # %c" \ 
     -o gpx -F out.gpx
</screen>
         <para> MERGE</para>
         <para> Merge puts all track points into one single track and
         sort them by time. Points with identical time stamp will be
         dropped !!!</para>
         <para> If you want to merge tracks from different devices but
         from same trip, use this:</para>
         <screen format="linespecific">
gpsbabel -t \
     -i gpx -f john.gpx \
     -i gpx -f doe.gpx \
     -x track,merge,title="COMBINED LOG" \
     -o gpx -F john_doe.gpx
</screen>
	<para>FIX</para>
	<para>Fix forces the GPS fix status for all trackpoints to the 
        specified value.  The value may be PPS, DGPS, 3D, 2D, or NONE.
	</para>
	<screen format="linespecific">
	gpsbabel -i gpx -f trk.gpx -x track,fix=3D -o nmea -F -
	</screen>

	<para>COURSE</para>
	<para>Course computes a value for the GPS heading at each trackpoint.
	This is most useful with trackpoints from formats that don't support
	heading information or for trackpoints synthesized by the interpolate
	filter.  The heading at each trackpoint is simply the course from the
	previous trackpoint in the track.  The first trackpoint in each track
        is arbitrarily assigned a heading of 0 degrees.</para>
	<screen format="linespecific">
	gpsbabel -i gpx -f trk.gpx -x track,course,speed -o nmea -F -
	</screen>

	<para>SPEED</para>
	<para>Course computes a value for the GPS speed at each trackpoint.
	This is most useful with trackpoints from formats that don't support
	speed information or for trackoints synthesized by the interpolate
	filter.  The speed at each trackpoint is the average speed from the
	previous trackpoint (distance/time).  The first trackpoint in each
	track is assigned a speed of "unknown."</para>
	<screen format="linespecific">
	gpsbabel -i gpx -f trk.gpx -x track,course,speed -o nmea -F -
	</screen>

      
