<para> 
Many <ulink url="http://www.lowrance.com">Lowrance</ulink> systems have the ability
to output their data to an external storage device.
Early models (such as iFinder Hunt) supported an MMC card.
Newer models (HDS, Hook, Hook2, etc) support either an SD card or a microSD card.
When exported the data is saved to the card as a
file which can be read by your computer.
</para>

<para>
<ulink url="http://www.lowrance.com">Lowrance</ulink> has defined five distinct versions of USR files.
Some USR formats also have multiple element versions (i.e. USR version 4 has two versions of route data).
Depending on the model of device you have you may be able to specify export data in any of the
five USR formats and some models also support exporting data in GPX format. 

The following describes the multiple USR formats (this was copied from a recent Lowrance User Manual).
<para>
          User Data File version 6 - 
            This is used to import and export waypoints, routes and colored Trails.
</para>
<para>
          User Data File version 5 - 
            This is used to import and export waypoints and routes with a
            standardized universally unique identifier (UUID), which is very
            reliable and easy to use. The data includes such information as
            the time and date when a route was created, and so on.
</para>
<para>
          User Data File version 4 - 
            This is best used when transferring data from one system to
            another, since it contains all the extra bits of information these
            systems store about items.
</para>
<para>
          User Data File version 3 (w/depth) - 
            Should be used when transferring user data from one system to
            a legacy product (Lowrance LMS, LCX, and so on.)
</para>
<para>
          User Data File version 2 (no depth) - 
            Can be used when transferring user data from one system to a
            legacy product (Lowrance LMS, LCX, and so on.)
</para>
<para>
          GPX (GPS Exchange, no depth) - 
            This is the format most used on the web that shares amoung
            most GPS systems in the world.  Use this format if you are taking
            data to a competitors unit.
</para>
</para>

<para>
All systems support various numbers of waypoints, routes, and tracks.
Some early systems also supported event icon markers.
Event icon markers are represented by symbol, name, latitude and longitude data only.
By default, event icon markers are converted to waypoints on read.  You have the option to ignore event icon markers.
On write, you have the option to create event icon markers using waypoint data.
</para>
    
