<para>
   The format garmin_gpi supports the binary POI (.gpi) files that are useable
   on newer Garmin GPS receivers.  See <link linkend="fmt_garmin_poi">garmin_poi</link> for additional information about Garmin's own Poiloader program.
   <ulink url="http://www.garmin.com/support/agree.jsp?id=927">Garmin POI-Loader</ulink> is the standard application that creates GPI files
   with all possible features.
</para>
<para>
  Some of the third party and commercial GPI files are using some kind of
  encryption or compression that makes the file contents completely unreadable
  to us. If you get an error "Unsupported code page NNN. File is likely
   encrypted." means we could basically recognize it as a Garmin GPI file,
   but it's mangled beyond what we're likely to successfully read.
</para>
<para>
   The layout of GPI files isn't documented and our module was created
   via reverse engineering. If you get a problem on reading or writing 
   a GPI file, please provide that file (mailto:gpsbabel-misc@lists.sourceforge.net).
</para>
<para>
   At this time we don't support special features as "Tour-Guide" or links
   to sounds and pictures.
</para>
<important>
<para>
   Creation timestamp issue: See the option <link linkend="fmt_garmin_gpi">sleep</link> !!!
</para>
<para>
	This module does not support direct transfer of .GPI files to
	receivers in Garmin protocol mode.  For units like Nuvi, Zumo, or 
	Streetpilot, just choose a file that's on the drive where your
	GPS is mounted.   For units like the X series (GPSMap 60CSx, GPSMap 60Cx, Legend Hcx, etc.) 
	you must explictly put the unit in mass storage mode or mount
	the memory chip in an external reader and transfer the file 
	directly.
</para>
</important>
<example id="all_garmin_gpi_options">
  <title>Command showing garmin_gpi output example</title>
  <para>
    <userinput>
      gpsbabel -i gpx -f "My Points.gpx" -o garmin_gpi,category="Nice Restaurants",bitmap=restaurant.bmp,notes -F "My Points.gpi"
    </userinput>
  </para>
</example>
