<para>Serial download protocol for GPS data loggers based on Skytraq Venus 5 and Venus 6 chipsets.
If your logger came with the Windows software iTravelTech GPS Photo Tagger, chances are that you can
use this format to read its memory.</para>

<para>Following a list of devices which should be supported by this module
(Note that not all of them have actually been tested, so if you can confirm that additional models work, please mail the gpsbabel-misc group with your success, tips, and any pertinent links for your model.):</para>

<table id="skytraq_devices">
<title>Devices supported by skytraq module</title>
<tgroup cols="4">
<thead>
<row>
 <entry>Manufacturer</entry> 
 <entry>Model</entry> 
 <entry>USB (baud)</entry> 
 <entry>Bluetooth (baud)</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
  <entry>SJA</entry>
  <entry>"3-in-1" GPS logger</entry>
  <entry>up to 230400</entry>
  <entry>9600</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Navilock</entry>
  <entry>BT-455PDL</entry>
  <entry>untested</entry>
  <entry>untested</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Polaris</entry>
  <entry>Travel Honey</entry>
  <entry>up to 230400</entry>
  <entry>9600</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Pearl Diffusion</entry>
  <entry>Keymate STV-5</entry>
  <entry>untested</entry>
  <entry>untested</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Canmore</entry>
  <entry>GT-750F</entry>
  <entry>untested</entry>
  <entry>untested</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>Adapt Mobile</entry>
  <entry>Keychain Pro</entry>
  <entry>untested</entry>
  <entry>untested</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<example id="skytraq-on-linux">
  <title>Command showing skytraq download of tracks and erasing the logger on Linux</title>
  <para><userinput>gpsbabel -i skytraq,erase -f /dev/ttyUSB0 -o gpx -F out.gpx</userinput></para>
</example>

<para>If available, reading the logger using bluetooth should also work. However, many devices support only one
specific baud rate over bluetooth, e.g. 9600:</para>
<example id="skytraq-on-linux-bt">
  <title>Command showing skytraq download tracks via bluetooth on Linux</title>
  <para><userinput>rfcomm bind 0 &lt;bdaddr&gt;</userinput>
  <userinput>gpsbabel -i skytraq,baud=9600 -f /dev/rfcomm0 -o gpx -F out.gpx</userinput></para>
</example>

<para>The "initbaud" option might be helpful if autodetection fails or takes too long. With this option you
can tell GPSBabel the baud rate the device is currently set to. In contrast, the option "baud" specifies
the rate at which the actual download should take place. If it is different than "initbaud" (or the autodetected
rate, if initbaud wasn't given), the initial setting will be restored after finishing the download.</para>

<para>If read-at-once >= 1, batch mode is enabled with that many sectors being read at a time.
Under normal circumstances, the larger this number the faster the transfer.
Reducing "read-at-once" might help when you get transmission errors/aborts.
This option only applies to Venus 6 devices; Venus 5 devices always use read-at-once = 0.</para>
